Siavash Barqi-Janiar

SiavashBarqi@gmail.com • 647-745-1301 • linkedin.com/in/SiavashBarqiJaniar • SiavashBarqiJaniar.github.io

Summary

I am a **ML Researcher / Data Scientist** with a strong enterprise-level and academic background. My programming skills include **Python, C/C++, R, Matlab**, etc. I also have a solid research background, **5 publications**, and multiple awarded **scholarships**.

Experience

Data Engineer | Docma

Jan. 2024 - Present

- Designed an ETL pipeline from 0 to 100% including a Command Line Interface (CLI), data preprocessing, alpha-lag-decay process, and exporting the results, predicting future sales attribution.
- Automated 80% of data workflows and minimized the need for manual intervention.
- Enabled importing and exporting data from/to four different sources: local, API, AWS S3, and PostgreSQL (PSQL) database.
- Implemented distinct visualization dashboards using Plotly and Dash to help board members and senior engineers interactive with for decision making.
- Developed predictive ML-based algorithms using Sci-Kit Learn to forecast future client sales, leading to a new \$500K contract acquisition for the company.
- Held client meetings to present product updates, address their needs, and ensure their concerns were resolved. Provided the team with updates on next steps required to meet client requests.

Researcher | Mitacs & York University

May 2023 - Feb. 2024

- Contributed in ML-based electric vehicles (EV) charging management in smart cities domain by proposing an evolutionary reinforcement learning (ERL) algorithm.
- Utilized TensorFlow and PyTorch for building an evolutionary calculation model to minimize EV charging costs based on the city electricity price movements.
- Received recognition for its innovative approach, winning an \$8000 prize for its contribution to sustainable transportation and smart city initiatives.

Research Assistant | York University

Sep. 2021 - Apr. 2023

- Proposed a transfer learning (TL) method based on feature extraction to predict jamming patterns in a communication network. Reduced the time complexity of the primary model by 30 times.
- Realized a comprehensive XAI method comprising pattern recognition and rule learning for network security. Improved the transparency of the model compared to the benchmark explainable models by 17%, whilst having a 32% less error rate.
- Introduced an evaluation environment comparing the performance of Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) structures utilizing Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) layers, achieving a 13% higher throughput rate than Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) structures while having x1.2 fewer parameters.
- Peer Reviewed and presented multiple research papers throughout the work period.

Research Assistant | Amirkabir University

Jan. 2021 - Jun. 2021

- Realized an efficient model-free reinforcement learning MAC protocol for frequency resource allocation. Surpassed the benchmark protocol with nearly 60% better throughput.
- Leveraged an online actor-critic algorithm for access problems in heterogeneous networks.
 Achieved 95% throughput in the network marked as the highest possible performance.
- Optimized the resource allocation system in distributed computer networks with prioritized packets using ML/AI, which increased the throughput of the wireless system by approximately 15%.

Publications [Link]

- S. B. Janiar, P. Wang, "Intelligent Anti-jamming based on Deep Reinforcement Learning and Transfer Learning," IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology, 2023.
- Barqi Janiar S, Pourahmadi V, "Deep-reinforcement learning for fair distributed dynamic spectrum access in priority buffered heterogeneous wireless networks," *IET Commun. 2021;19*. https://doi.org/10.1049/cmu2.12098
- S. B. Janiar, P. Wang, "A transfer learning approach based on integrated feature extractor for anti-jamming in wireless networks," *IEEE PIMRC, Toronto*, 2023.
- S. B. Janiar, Xian Lu, P. Wang, "Explainable Reinforcement Learning for Wireless Security at the Physical Layer: A Survey," IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 2022.
- S. B. Janiar and V. Pourahmadi, "Deep-Reinforcement Learning for Fair Distributed Dynamic Spectrum Access in Wireless Networks," 2021 IEEE 18th Annual Consumer Communications & Networking Conference (CCNC), 2021, pp. 1-4, doi:
 - 10.1109/CCNC49032.2021.9369536.
- S. B. Janiar, A. Eckford, "The Theory and Applications of Coded Modulation in Digital Communications: A Survey", York University, Dec. 2021.

Projects [Link]

RAG based chatbot: [https://siaschatbot.streamlit.app/]

- Developed a RAG-based web app capable of retrieving information from any website, and answering questions based on the website information.
- Used Langchain and OpenAl's GPT-3.5 LLM model for the implementation.

Spam Email Detector:

- o Prompt engineered the Meta LLAMA 2 model for spam email detection using LangChain.
- Wrote a customized prompt code and used GCP for GPU-based training and evaluation.

MNIST Handwritten Digits

- Designed and implemented a supervised learning algorithm to classify handwritten digits using the MNIST dataset, achieving high accuracy in prediction.
- Optimized model performance by fine-tuning hyperparameters, applying feature engineering techniques, and utilizing regularization methods to reduce overfitting.
- Developed and trained the model using Keras and TensorFlow, leveraging a CNN for improved digit recognition.

Education

York University | MS Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

Field of Study: Al and Machine Learning

Amirkabir University | BS Electrical Engineering

Focus: Telecom Engineering, AI, and Machine Learning GPA: 3.4 / 4.0

2023

2021

GPA: 3.8 / 4.0

Skills

- Programming Languages: Python, SQL, C/C++, Java, R, HTML, JavaScript, C#.
- LLM / ML Frameworks: Sci-kit Learn, PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, LLAMA, LangChain, HuggingFace, Chroma, Spark MLib.
- ML Techniques: Supervised Learning, Unsupervised Learning, Deep-Reinforcement Learning
- Cloud Tools: AWS, Docker, Google Compute Engine, Google Cloud Storage.
- o API and Visualization Tools: Streamlit, Kivy, Matplotlib, Git, LaTeX, Qt Design.